Good morning. Today's דף *daf* is י *Yud* and we pick up
with the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. And this is going to be, I
think, one of the משניות *Mishnayot* you will probably remember for many,
many years to come. So let's take a look at it.
No, no, I actually mean that quite seriously. All right, let's take
a look. So we had a משנה mishnah. *Mishnah* before about somebody
saying I'm a נזיר nazir *nazir* from dates and whether that's how
that was interpreted. But anyway, here's this משנה mishnah *Mishnah*. אמר *Amar*,
a guy says. אמר פרה para *Amar para*, this cow said, זו
*zo*, this cow said, הריני נזירה Hareini nezirah, *Hareini nezira*, I the
cow will be a נזירה nezira *nezira*. אם עומדת im omedet *Im
omedet*, if she stands. Okay, אם עומדת אני im omedet ani? *im
omedet ani*, excuse me, if I stand. Okay, that's what the cow
says, like a Far Side cartoon.
And the cow's the thing that's saying it?
That's what the guy is coming, the guy's coming and telling us
according to this משנה mishnah. *Mishnah*: "Hey, I saw this cow who
said that she'll be a נזירה nezira *nezira* if she stands." Okay,
so or אומר הדלת *omer hadelet*, this door said, הזה *hazeh*, הריני
נזירה hareini nezirah אם נפתח אני ani. *Hareini nezira im niftach ani*.
The door, I saw this door said, I'll be a נזירה nezira?
*nezira* if I open, if I'm opened. Okay, so what's the story?
So the story is this guy needs his meds or something. בית
שמאי Beit Shammai. אומרים *Beis Shammai omrim*, בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis
Shammai* says, נזיר nazir, *Nazir*, you're a נזיר nazir. *nazir*, not the
cow or the door, you.
And only if it's open or if the cow...
Well, who knows. ובית הלל אומרים *Ubeish Hillel omrim*, let's say it's
open, who knows. ובית הלל אומרים *Ubeish Hillel omrim* we'll see in
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. אינו נזיר nazir *Eino nazir*. I'm not a
נזיר nazir *nazir*. אמר רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Amar Rabbi Yehuda*, אף
כשאמרו בית שמאי Beit Shammai *af keshe'amru Beis Shammai*, even when בית
שמאי Beit Shammai. *Beis Shammai* said he's a נזיר nazir *nazir*, they
didn't really mean he's a נזיר nazir *nazir*. לא lo, אמרו אלא
באומר הרי פרה para זו עלי קרבן korban, אם עומדת omedet היא
*Lo amru ela ba'omer harei para zo alai korban im omedet hi*.
They really meant that the cow is forbidden to me, sort of
like when the guy said I'm a נזיר nazir, *nazir* from the
דבילה *develah*, he doesn't really become a נזיר nazir *nazir*, it means
that the dates are forbidden to him. So here too, it's not
really a נזיר nazir, *nazir*, the cow is forbidden to me. I
don't know what it would mean by the door. The door is
forbidden to him, something like that. Okay, as if that were our
biggest concern, which was: do you mean a נזיר nazir *nazir* or
do you mean the thing is forbidden to you? It's like what
the heck is going on with the cow saying that it's a
נזיר nazir *nazir*? So let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. Now, obviously that's what bothers the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but what
the... how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually answers the question and where
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* winds up is itself a bit of a
riddle. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says:
פרה מי קא משתעיא *Para mi ka mishtaya*? Since when does a
cow talk? Okay, good question. At least it asks, only horses talk.
At least it asks the right question.
Okay, so אמר רמי *Amar Rami*, אמר רמי בר חמא *Amar Rami
bar Chama*, it says רמי בר חמא *Rami bar Chama*. הכא במאי
עסקינן *Hacha bemai askinan*, what are we talking about? כגון שהייתה פרה
רבוצה לפניו *Kegon shehayesa para revutza lefanav*. There was a cow that
was crouched down in front of you. ואמר *Ve'amar*, and you said:
כסבורה פרה זו אינה עומדת *Kisvura
para zo eina omedet*. This cow must be thinking that it's not
going to be able to stand up. It looks like it's really
crouched down in a serious way, it's thinking that it's not able
to stand. I'll tell you what, הריני נזיר מבשרה Hareini Nazir mib’sarah.
*Hareini nazir mibesara*, I will be a נזיר nazir. *nazir* from its
flesh, and therefore making it a parallel to the earlier משנה mishnah?
*Mishnah*, I'm a נזיר nazir *nazir* from these dates, which allows the
position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* in the end that
says you're not really a נזיר nazir *nazir*, you're forbidden from the
פרה *para*. So first of all you said I will be a
נזיר nazir. *nazir* from its flesh אם עמדה amda מאליה mealeha. *im
amda me'aleha*, if it stands up on its own. ועמדה מאליה *Ve'amda
me'aleha*, and it stood up on its own. So basically you made
this weird condition. Oh, it looks like this cow doesn't want to
stand up, I'll be a נזיר nazir. *nazir* from its flesh if
it stands. And then it went and it stood. So then what's
the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel* and בית שמאי
Beit Shammai, *Beis Shammai*? Same debate as the previous משנה mishnah. *Mishnah*,
because what does it mean to be a נזיר nazir *nazir* from
the meat of a cow? ואזלו בית שמאי Beit Shammai לשיטתם ובית
הלל לשיטתם *Ve'azlu Beis Shammai leshitasan veBeis Hillel leshitasan*. And we're just
going to read this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* straight and then I want
to go back and say how you even read this in the
משנה mishnah *Mishnah*. But basically what he did is he completely reduced
any of the sort of interesting parts of that משנה mishnah *Mishnah*
to basically boil down to the fact that a guy said I'm
going to be a נזיר nazir *nazir* from the meat of this
cow if the cow stands. And then the question is what does
that mean to be a נזיר nazir. *nazir* from the meat of
this cow? So בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis Shammai* says you're a
נזיר nazir. *nazir*, בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel* says you're not.
It's just like the discussion about the dates. What... okay. So the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is going to say: בית שמאי Beit Shammai דאמרי
*Beis Shammai de'amri*, בית שמאי Beit Shammai. *Beis Shammai* says: מן הגרוגרת
ומן הדבילה הוי נזיר nazir *Min hagroggeres umin hadevelah havei nazir*.
That if a guy says I'm a נזיר nazir *nazir* from the
dates and pressed and dried dates, you're a נזיר nazir *nazir*. And
we somehow drop the dates part and we just focus on the
נזיר nazir *nazir* part. הכא נמי *Hacha nami*, here too, כי אמר
מבשרה *ki amar mibesara*, when I say I'm a נזיר nazir, *nazir*
from the meat of the cow, הוי נזיר nazir *havei nazir*, he's
a נזיר nazir. *nazir*. ובית הלל אמרי *UBeis Hillel amri*, and בית
הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel* says, לא lo, הוי נזיר nazir *lo
havei nazir*, you're not a נזיר nazir. *nazir* because there's no such
thing as being a נזיר nazir *nazir* from dates
or from meat. And therefore your whole sentence is meaningless. Or the
way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said it before, maybe it's like a
sentence with the פתח עמו *pesach imo*, you're clearly חוזר *chozer*. Whatever
it is, it's a meaningless sentence and you're not bound by it.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: So why do we need them
to debate that again? ואמר בית שמאי Beit Shammai, חדא זימנא *Ve'amar
Beis Shammai chada zimna*, בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis Shammai* said it
before about the dates. אמר רבא Amar Rava, *Amar Rava*, תרי תלת
*trei telas*, yeah, two or three times we're telling you the variations
of the same idea. וכן תני רבי חייא *Vechein tani Rabbi Chiya*,
and that's what רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiya* taught. תרתי תלת, you know,
two or three times we're telling you the same idea that if
you say you're a נזיר nazir from X, and X is something
weird like meat or dates or whatever, it's a debate of בית
הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai Okay, וכן אמר רבי
יאשיה תרתי תלת, v'chen amar Rabbi Yoshiya tarti tlas, Rabbi Yoshiya also
said two or three times yesterday giving variations of the same debate.
וצריכא. u'tzricha. Now, that's not a full answer to why... wonderful, it's
two or three times, but still, why keep on why give more
and more illustrations? What does that do for you? דאי איתמר בהא,
de'i itmar b'ha, if you had just said the case of גרוגרות
ודבלה grogros u'dveilah in the case in the first משנה mishnah by
the dates case that בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you're a נזיר,
nazir? התם הוא דאמרי בית שמאי הוי נזיר. hasam hu de'amri Beit
Shammai havei nazir. That's why בית שמאי Beis Shammai says you're a
נזיר. nazir Right? משום דמיחלפן בענבים. mishum demichalfin ba'anavim. Dates and grapes,
it's all pretty similar. Okay, it's fruit, it's they're smallish or whatever,
they're darkish. Alright, it's all pretty similar. And therefore, you know, you
got in your head that the same way the תורה Torah says
that a נזיר nazir. can't eat grapes, you got in your head
that it actually means dates. Okay, actually they do look somewhat similar
I guess, I mean dates are a little bit longer. Okay, anyway.
So you got those confused. So we'll say bottom line, you wanted
to be a נזיר nazir and that's why it works. Okay, that's
a more understandable position of בית שמאי. Beis Shammai אבל בשר בענבים.
aval basar ba'anavim. Nobody gets in their head that grapes and wine
are the same thing. Meat and wine, excuse me, grapes and wine.
Meat and wine, or meat and grapes, excuse me. לא מיחלף. lo
michalaf. That people don't get mixed up. So if you said meat,
I would think that it's meaningless. So ואי איתמר בשר, ve'i itmar
basar, if you had just told me the case of meat, I
would say, no, actually that doesn't make sense. הכא הוא דאמרי בית
שמאי הוי נזיר. hacha hu de'amri Beit Shammai havei nazir. Actually, it
makes sense that you're a נזיר nazir if you say you're a
נזיר nazir from meat. Why? בבישרא וחמרא. bevishra vechamra. Because that's meat
and wine go together, right? What is a nice good meal except
a good steak with a good glass of red wine? So okay,
so you know the תורה Torah says, and by the way, it's
not as crazy as it sounds because you
know, it's like when the, right, ascetic, right, ascetic, ascetic. Right, when
people think about a נזיר, nazir they think about asceticism, they think
about self-denial and type of indulgence, right? So wine is like a
very sensual, like, you know, food type of indulgence. So it wouldn't
be so crazy to think, oh yeah, נזיר nazir can't drink wine,
can't eat meat. Like there are times, by the way, that you're
not supposed to. דאמר מר, de'amar mar, as the מר mar says,
wine and meat... somebody, right, that's like, you know, an אונן onen
isn't supposed to drink wine and eat meat. Right? That's a certain
type of, those do go together as a certain type of like
classic sort of physical indulgence. Now it's actually interesting that the תורה
Torah does not... you know, that is a common belief, right? That
the נזיר, nazir? what he symbolizes is asceticism. Actually it's worth noting
that, you know, that's not exactly... wine is not just about the
sort of physical pleasure, right? Wine is about the fact that it
gives you like a high and it makes you like, you know,
maybe clouds your thinking, right? So how much is the נזיר nazir
forswearing of wine, or how much is the fact the נזיר nazir
forbidden from wine... right, you know, like when the תורה Torah says...
what's the פסוק pasuk in... No, no, no, yeah that I know,
but what's the פסוק, pasuk, is it in ישעיהו? Yeshayahu? ירמיהו? Yirmiyahu?
It says that that you made my נזירים nezirim drink wine ולנביאים
אמרו לא תנבאו. u'linevi'im amru lo tinavu. What is that פסוק? pasuk?
ותשקו את הנזירים יין ועל הנביאים צויתם לאמר לא תנבאו. vatashku es
hanezirim yayin ve'al hanevi'im tzivisem leimor lo tinavu. Like you know, you
get my נזירים nezirim drunk. Right? It's not just the problem of
the physical indulgence, it's that, you know, it's that it's distracting them
from devoting their full intellectual capacities to serving God. So anyway, so
it's interesting, the that association, right? Of wine and meat is not
crazy and it's interesting about thinking about that in terms of a
נזיר. nazir, So if somebody had said, "That's it, I'm a נזיר
Nazir from meat," we could understand how they got in their head
that that's what a נזיר Nazir is about, it's about wine and
meat, and basically they really wanted to be a נזיר. Nazir. So
maybe that works because deep down they wanted to be a נזיר.
Nazir Okay, so that would have made sense. אבל גרוגרות ודבלה, aval
grogros u'dveilah, but I would have thought if you said I'm a
נזיר Nazir, from from dates, לא, lo then that's a crazy idea.
No normal person thinks that's what a נזיר Nazir, is about. So
obviously you didn't really want to be a נזיר. Nazir קא משמע
לן ka mashma lan that even in that case I'll say that
deep down you wanted to be a נזיר. Nazir ואי תנא הני
תרתי, ve'i tana hanei tarti, and if he had given me these
two examples for בית שמאי, Beis Shammai נזיר Nazir from dates and
a נזיר Nazir from wine... so I would have
said... הני הוא דקאמרי בית שמאי, hanei hu deka'amri Beit Shammai, maybe
in those cases I get
it, because did I say dates and wine?
I just said
that, dates and meat, excuse me. See, now you see why I
would say they're mistakes so everybody... I just... okay. Anyway, so if
you give me just the case by dates and the case by
meat, I would have said in both of those cases I get
why בית שמאי Beis Shammai says you're a נזיר Nazir because there's
a way in which people make those
associations. אבל דלת, aval deles, if somebody said I'm a נזיר Nazir
from this door, what the heck does that mean? אימא מודי להו
לבית הלל, eima modi lehu l'Beit Hillel, maybe they would agree to
בית הלל Beit Hillel that that's complete nonsense and that's not binding.
Okay, and nevertheless, no, they say it even by a door, once
you said you're a נזיר, Nazir even if the end of the
sentence doesn't make sense, we ignore it. ואי תנא דלת, ve'i tana
deles, had he just said door, בהא קאמרי בית הלל. beha ka'amri
Beit Hillel. Why? That's the case that בית הלל Beit Hillel says
that you are not a נזיר Nazir because that's complete nonsense. אבל
בהנך תרתי אימא מודי להו לבית שמאי, aval behanach tarti eima modi
lehu l'Beit Shammai, but maybe they might agree in one of the
cases about dates or the case... about meat, for reasons we said,
that maybe that is a guy really does want to be a
נזיר. Nazir קא משמע לן דלא. Ka mashma lan d'lo. And it's
telling me not. So it's giving all these three cases to say
even in the most absurd cases בית שמאי Beis Shammai says you
are a נזיר Nazir and even in the cases where the guy
could be making an honest mistake, בית הלל Beit Hillel says you're
not a נזיר. Nazir. Now all of that is quite lovely, which
completely ignores the colorful
description, the scenario in the beginning of the משנה. mishnah It just
gets down to the fact like don't let this whole משנה mishnah
of the talking cow distract you, right? All we're really saying is
the guy said I'm a נזיר Nazir. from the meat of a
cow, or a guy said I'm a נזיר Nazir from a דלעת.
dela'at. And it's really just a variation of the previous משנה. Mishna
Okay, but what do you do with the crazy משנה? Mishna And
what do you mean you said I am saying I will be
a נזיר? Nazir That's not what you said. You said the cow
is saying אמרה פרה זו הריני נזירה. Amra para zu hareni nezira.
I'm going to be a נזיר Nazir if I stand up. So
how do you just read those words? So very interesting תוספות Tosafot
which tries really valiantly to make sense of this משנה. Mishna So
the first thing תוספות Tosafot speaks about, if he says, what we're
dealing here with is anthropomorphism, meaning that you project human the way
you think onto the onto these inanimate objects. And basically since people
think that it looks like the cow doesn't want to stand, the
way you describe it is the cow is saying it's not going
to stand. Okay, not like it's literally saying that, but that's anthropomorphic,
right? So what you're saying is, look, look at the cow. It's
basically telling us it doesn't want to stand, right? So so he
actually quotes an interesting פסוק pasuk from from יונה, Yonah, getting a
little bit in יונה דיומא Yonah deYoma where it says, getting close
to יום כיפור Yom Kippur where it says, והאניה חשבה להישבר. veha'oniyah
chishvah lehishaver. What is it? חשבה להישבר, chishvah lehishaver, right? And the
boat was planning on breaking, thought that it would break. Right, the
boat wasn't thinking that it would break. It's a way of saying
the boat was about to break, but the word used here is
it thought that. So the cow said it's not going up. Okay,
so it's one thing to say the cow is said is telling
us it's not going to stand, it doesn't want to stand. But
that's still not the cow telling us that it's a נזיר. Nazir,
How does that work? So basically what תוספות Tosafot says is okay,
he says אמרה פרה זו, Amra para zu, okay, I'm no I'm
just reading the משנה Mishna but I'm filling in the lines now
for תוספות. Tosafot. אמרה פרה זו, Amra para zu, this cow is
telling us something. It's telling us that it looks like it doesn't
want to stand. That's what a cow's looking telling us. Now that's
the end of now we get to a new statement. Then the
guy says הריני נזירה אם עומדת. Hareini nezira im omedet. I'll be
a נזיר Nazir if it stands. Now there's a little bit of
a problem. The problem is נזירה nezira is feminine. So this is
brilliant. You know what תוספות Tosafot says? He says what? A woman
talking? No, that could be, but he doesn't say that, then it
would be אמרה, amrah, the first would be אמרה, amrah, and then.
No, he says the ה, hei, ready for this grammarians here? Is
a מפיק ה. mapik hei. הריני נזירה, nezira I am a נזיר
ממנה, nazir mimena, I am a נזיר Nazir. from the cow. So
that's how you get the idea that the guy is saying I'm
a נזיר Nazir from the meat. You turn the ה hei into
a מפיק ה. mapik hei. That's pretty brilliant.
That's the way I read it the first time.
I'm sure it is, right, exactly.
So מפיק's Mapik are very important.
Of course, of course. So okay so what so so we're try
so אמרה פרה זו, Amra para zu, this cow is telling us
something, but it doesn't have what it's telling us. This cow is
telling us that it doesn't want to stand. That's what this cow
is telling us. So you know what? הריני נזיר הימנה, Hareini nazir
heimena, I will be a נזיר Nazir from its meat אם עומדת
if it stands. Now the only word that doesn't fit is אני.
ani So what's אם עומדת אני? Because the guy it's the cow
standing, it's not me standing. So it doesn't all right we gotta
say that the אני means I don't know and I am going
to be a נזיר Nazir if it happens or something like he
he gets caught up on that last word, but it was so
good. Anyway, that's how תוספות Tosafot valiantly tries to fit that into
the גמרא. Gemara, The other approach of תוספות Tosafot is to take
the משנה Mishna more seriously and to actually say that this guy
is basically reporting that this is what this cow said. And since
that's complete nonsense, we translate
that as
why is this guy telling us that this cow said that it
would be a נזיר? Nazir It must be a funny way of
the guy telling us that he wants to be a נזיר Nazir
from the cow. Okay, so that at least is taking the משנה
Mishna. at face value. Of course, what תוספות Tosafot said is then
the חידוש chiddush of this משנה Mishna. is not the debate of
בית שמאי
בית הלל, Beit Shammai Beit Hillel, what happens when you say I'm
a נזיר Nazir, from the meat, whether it works. The חידוש chiddush
is that if a guy tells you a story about a cow,
you translate it as to be a story about accepting נזירות. nezirut.
Oh fine, but anyway, but at
least imagine those talking animals.
Exactly, thank you.
Yes, I have a friend saying,
there you go, I'm a cow, I have a friend cow who
said it wanted to be a נזיר, Nazir wanted to know your
advice, right. So anyway, very good. Okay, so it said
okay
take a look, we'll just read that that interpretation because at least
it's not as brilliant as the first one, but at least it
you know treats the משנה Mishna in its פשט pshat way. So
if you look at it, it's like five lines. before the lines
get to be middle-sized in תוספות, Tosfos, where the line starts with
like איש ירושלים, Ish Yerushalayim, sort of where it says רב רב
יוסף איש ירושלים פירוש דהכי פירושה דמתניתין. Rav Rav Yosef Ish Yerushalayim
pirush de hachi pirusha de masnisin. אמר פירוש אמר האדם כשראה פרה
רבוצה, Amar pirush amar hadam kesheraha para revutza, man said when he
saw this crouched down cow, כמדומה אני, kemidume ani, it looks to
me דאמרה פרה זו, de'amra para zu, that this cow is saying
הריני נזירה אם עומדת. hareni nezira im omedet. It looks to me
like this cow is saying that it's going to be a נזירה
if it stands up, שהיא תאבת לעמוד ואינה
יכולה. she'i toevet la'amod ve'eina yechola. Now why would a cow say
that? Because obviously it's trying to stand up, so it's sort of
this cow is making a deal with God that, God, if you
let me stand I'll be a נזיר nazir or something, ואינה יכולה
וברצון תדור נזירות אם תעמוד. ve'eina yechola uviratzon tidor nezirut im ta'amod.
The cow is prepared to be a נזיר nazir. if it could
only stand up. So anyway that's his story about the cow. אם
תעמודני. im ta'amodni. So then he says אם תעמוד אני אשלים בעדיה.
im ta'amod ani aslim va'adeha.
You know what? I'll take that נזירות nezirut responsibility off for the
cow. The cow shouldn't have to be a
נזיר. nazir כי הריני נזיר מבשרה אם תעמוד, ki hareni nazir mivesara
im ta'amod, because I'll be a נזיר nazir if it stands. So
anyway actually he didn't say that you totally just said what the
cow is saying, he actually
said that you then fill in the blank. Okay, but then later
תוספות Tosfos says maybe you didn't even fill in the blank. ונראה
לפרש, venira lefareish, now if you go down one two three four
five lines down in the middle-sized lines near the end of the
line, ונראה לפרש, venira lefareish, but it looks like you should explain
שאין אדם אומר כלום. she'ein adam omer klum. He's not filling in
the key line and saying that he's saying he'll be a
נזיר, nazir רק שהיה מספר מילתא דפרה. rak shehaya mesaper milta depara.
He was telling us a story about a cow. You heard about
fish stories? This was a cow story.
Okay. מילתא דפרה ולא שייך בו נזירות. milta depara velo shayach bo
nezirut. Now of course a cow can't be a
נזיר, nazir, רק שתהא מופרשת לאיסורה. rak shetei mufreshet le'issura. We'll interpret
what do you mean when you're trying to tell us that the
cow said it would be a נזירה? What you mean is you
don't want to eat from the meat of the
cow, שלא יהנה מבשרה. shelo yeihane mivesara. היכא דאדם מספר לפנינו, heichach
kesheadam mesaper lefaneinu, when you're telling us this weird story of a
cow, כך בדעתו לקיים עליו שיהא נזיר מבשרה. kach bedaito lekayem alav
sheyehe nazir mivesara. What you're really telling us is that you want
to be a נזיר nazir from the meat. So that's taking the
משנה Mishna? literal at face value and saying yeah it's an absurd
thing to say, and what we're going to interpret it to mean
is you're saying that you want to be a נזיר nazir from
the meat. The only thing is, is that then why does the
גמרא Gemara focus besides he didn't say the magic words? That's a
יד, yad, whatever it is. Okay. He doesn't have to say them
if that's what you mean. But the question is why does the
גמרא Gemara focus on the fact that then the point of the
משנה Mishna is to tell us, oh by the way the debate
of בית שמאי בית הלל Beis Shammai Beis Hillel didn't only apply
by dates it also applied by meat and doors. The biggest חידוש
chiddush of the משנה Mishna is that we interpret this crazy story
to mean a statement of נזירות. nezirut. Okay, so anyway what the
גמרא Gemara is doing is it's basically saying like bracketing the whole
crazy story in the beginning of the משנה Mishna and boiling it
down to the debate about a guy says I'm a נזיר nazir
from dates, I'm a נזיר nazir from wine, excuse me, I'm a
נזיר nazir from dates, I'm a נזיר nazir from meat, I'm a
נזיר nazir from a door and ignores the crazy story with the
cow. Okay. But again so either we're taking the משנה Mishna. literally
and that's how we interpret his crazy story or the very brilliant
read of תוספות Tosfos reading the נזירה with a מפיק ה, mappik
hey, which was a very valiant attempt to get this into the
משנה.
Mishnah Okay, נזירה with a מפיק ה. mappik hey.
פרה is feminine.
עומדת is feminine. אומרת הדלת הזאת omeret adeles hazos instead of אומר
והיא הדלת הזאת. omer vehi adeles hazos.
Just just weird, the tense right? It goes back from...
that's a good point. Okay, I don't know. All right. So that's
the first explanation of the גמרא. Gemara Now with all that explanation
let's see what bothers the גמרא Gemara with this. So the גמרא
Gemara now
continues, אמר רבא, Rava. so says
רבא. Rava מי קתני אם עמדה מאליה? mi ktani im amda me'eleha?
Wait wait wait. Here's my problem with that whole explanation. You said
the guy made a condition I'll be a נזיר nazir. from its
meat if the cow stands up on its own. But does it
say if it stands up on its own? It just says if
it stands up. So that can't be פשט pshat in the משנה.
Mishnah, Which is like what? Of all the things like of all
the crazy things that we sometimes read into a משנה Mishnah you
can't read in the word on its own? And besides which take
out that whole part. Just say the guy said I'll be a
נזיר nazir if it stands and it stood. Who needs to insert
the problem that you said on its own and then point out
oh it doesn't say on its own in the משנה? Mishnah. Right
what type of crazy question is that? So basically what תוספות Tosfos
says, I mean look this is like a really hard גמרא. Gemara
I mean just not hard like you know whatever it's like hard
to know what the גמרא Gemara is getting at. Anyway so תוספות
Tosfos basically says that's just a way of
saying I think that was a, I think this whole thing doesn't
make sense, that's a crazy פשט pshat in the משנה Mishnah because
because the משנה is talking about a story with a cow and
it's not just talking about you saying that you're not going to
eat the meat, that you're a נזיר nazir, from the meat. So
somehow the fact that the משנה doesn't say on its own רבא
Rava is using as a way of saying I don't like that
explanation. תוספות Tosfos says it's really just not the problem that it
didn't say the words on its own, it's just that he says
give me a break that's not what's going on in the משנה.
So let's see if רבא Rava does any better. Okay. אלא אמר
רבא, Ela amar Rava, so rather רבא says, כגון שהייתה פרה רבוצה
לפנינו, kigon shehayesa para revutza lefaneinu, we go back to the פרה
crouching down in front of us or I guess the case by
the דלת, deles, never gets around to the דלת deles but let's
say the דלת deles is stuck, the דלת deles is refusing to
open up and you say okay man this דלת deles looks like
it took a vow of
Okay, so the cow is crouch- I told you you're not going
to forget this משנה *Mishna*. It's straight out of a farce, you
know. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so the cow is
crouched down, ואמר *ve'amar* and you say, הרי עלי קרבן *Harei alay
korban*, this cow will be a קרבן *korban* to me. Now what?
First of all, you know, how, what do you do with the
beginning part of the משנה *Mishna*, and how does הרי עלי קרבן
*Harei alay korban* work for the door? So anyway, let's take a
look. And how is בית שמאי Beis Shammai *Beit Shammai* saying you're
a נזיר nazir *nazir* if you said הרי עלי קרבן *Harei alay
korban*, you're just making the cow forbidden? That doesn't explain בית שמאי
Beis Shammai *Beit Shammai*'s position that you're a נזיר nazir. *nazir*.
לפניו *Lefanav* means in front of
you, the guy who's talking, the person who's talking. Okay, so the
גמרא *Gemara* says one minute, so the גמרא *Gemara* quickly rejects this.
בשלמא פרה בר קרבן היא *Bishlama para bar korban hi*, if you
say this cow is a קרבן *korban* that works by cow, אלא
דלת בר קרבן היא *Ela delet bar korban hi*, doesn't work by
door. Of course you could say like קונם *Konam*, this door is
forbidden to me, doesn't have to literally be a קרבן *korban*, but
anyway it doesn't explain why בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* would say you're
a נזיר nazir, *nazir*, right? That would just get you to the
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* position, that the door or the
cow is forbidden to you. אלא אמר רבא כגון שהייתה פרה רבוצה
לפניו *Ela amar Rava kegon shehayta para revutza lefanav*, finally let's try
again. The cow is crouched down in front of you ואמר *ve'amar*
and you say הרי נזיר nazir מיין *Harei nazir miyayin*, so you
just say I'm going to be a straight נזיר nazir, *nazir* from
wine. Okay, so you took a normal נזירות nezirut *nezirot*. אם לא
עמדה im lo amda, *Im lo amda*, if the cow doesn't stand,
ועמדה מאליה *Ve'amda me'aleha* and it stood up on its own. Now
this gets complicated, because first of all, the first thing to point
out is the משנה *Mishna* said the cow said it'll be a
נזיר nazir *nazir* if it does stand, and רבא *Rava* is saying
you're saying the cow said it'll be a נזיר nazir *nazir* if
or you said you'll be a נזיר nazir *nazir* if the cow
doesn't stand. So it says well, I don't understand, you just gave
the previous explanation a hard time because it didn't have the word
ועמדה מאליה *Ve'amda me'aleha*. You stuck in a little word לא *lo*,
not. So how do you get away with that? Well you know,
sometimes a word לא *lo* might be missing, that's more of an
acceptable omission than the other one. Okay, I don't even understand what's
going on, fine. So first thing רבא *Rava* does is the משנה
*Mishna* says you say you'll be a נזיר nazir *nazir* if it
does stand, and you said you'll be a נזיר nazir *nazir* if
it doesn't stand. Fine, anyway what's going on? So it stood up
on its own, so you say you'll be a נזיר *nazir* if
it doesn't stand, it did stand, you shouldn't be a נזיר *nazir*.
So what's the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beit Hillel* and
בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* going on here? בית שמאי סברי *Beit Shammai
savri*, בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* holds תורצא דהאי גברא *tursa de-hai gavra*,
your focus is משום אוקמי בידיה הוא *mishum okmei biyadei hu*. When
you said I'll be a נזיר *nazir* if it doesn't stand, you
mean if I'm not able to raise it up, you really didn't
care whether it stood on its own or not, you meant like
if I'm not able to pick it up I'll be a נזיר
*nazir*. Again תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says where are we getting all of
this? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says we're trying to get into the
psychology of the guy, like why would you סתם *stam* say I'll
be a נזיר *nazir* if the thing doesn't stand, like what's relevant
there? But we could understand an idea which is like it's a
cow, you want to get it to stand up, you know you're
afraid that it's not going to stand up, this is sort of
like one of these deals with God. So you basically say like
if I wait does this work אם לא *im lo*, if I
don't get it to stand I'll be a נזיר *nazir*.
I bet you I can get it to stand, right,
so maybe it's that, right, like I will be able to get
it to stand, if I can't get it to stand I'll be
a נזיר *nazir*, some type of... that's what we're assuming his psychology
is. Okay, like he's trying to prove that he can get it
to stand, or he's saying if I can't get it to stand
I'll be a נזיר *nazir*. So we interpret his word if it
doesn't stand to mean if I can't get it to stand, and
therefore ולא אוקמה *ve-lo ukma*, your focus was that you'd be able
to get it to stand but you didn't get it to stand,
it stood by itself, so that wasn't your point. Your point was
that if you couldn't get it to stand you'd be a נזיר
*nazir*, not if it just didn't stand on its own. So in
the end of the day you know that wasn't... it wasn't like
you wait a minute how does this work? So in the end
of the day you didn't wait now I'm confused you didn't get
it to stand, okay, it stood on its own but you weren't
the one who got it to stand.
But he wanted it to stand, right?
No, so that's what בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* is saying. You say
if it doesn't stand I'm a נזיר *nazir*, but for some reason,
don't ask me why, בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* is interpreting what that
means: if it doesn't stand I'm a נזיר *nazir* means if I
can't get it to stand I'll be a נזיר *nazir*, and at
the end of the day you weren't the one who got it
to stand, so you're a נזיר *nazir*. That's what בית שמאי *Beit
Shammai*... wait let's just get through this. ובית הלל סברי u'Beis Hillel
savri, *U-Beit Hillel savri*, and בית הלל Beis Hillel *Beit Hillel* says
you didn't say if I wouldn't get it to stand, משום תרביעה
הוא *mishum terviahu*, it's crouched down, so you weren't talking about you
getting it to stand, you were just saying stand or not stand,
so הא קמה *ha kama* it stood, so it stood, you're not
a נזיר *nazir*. Now basically what we have done is, and I
still don't get it, we've completely again ignored this crazy beginning of
the משנה *Mishna*, the cow is saying this, the cow is saying
that. Okay, how do we know how to read that into the
משנה *Mishna*? And number two is we've switching a condition that's like
if where it says the cow says if I do stand to
you saying if it doesn't stand. We add the word doesn't and
then we make the whole
debate. Reinterpret every part of this משנה.
Yes, though actually, I don't know about putting in the word לא,
but as far as, sort of, trying to ascribe motives to the
cow, that would sort of be getting back to what the משנה
is saying.
Yeah, הפרה זו, ha-para zo,
like we're trying to ascribe autonomy to the cow in a way
by saying this cow is saying, that's similar to saying this cow
wants to get up, right? And I'm going to whatever.
Right, so, right, so that is similar, I mean, that's again the
way the תוספות Tosafot sort of explained according to the first approach
also. הפרה ha-para saying means the cow wants to, is trying to
stand, right, is trying to stand and it's not able to stand,
and if I can't get it to stand I'll be a נזיר.
So the point about the cow is saying הריני נזירה אם עומדת
hareini nezirah im omedet means the cow is trying to stand but
not succeeding, and I'll tell you what, I bet I'll be able
to get it to stand. And if I can't get it to
stand then I'll be a נזיר. That's sort of how the גמרא's
reading it. What תוספות's Tosafot with the הריני נזירה and do we
go by, you know, who's saying whether the cow's saying it or
you're saying it is correct. But it again, it is strange that
it sticks in this word לא and it makes the debate of
בית הלל Beis Hillel? and בית שמאי all about like a תנאי
tnai about which it doesn't sound like they're really debating.
Does it sound like anybody's bringing in the story of אליעזר? Eliezer?
Because it sounds to me a lot like that, right?
Oh, you mean the whole making the deal with God? Yeah, well,
that's, I mean, the גמרא, I tried to sort of, you know,
tell you what תוספות Tosafot said about the psychology that you're sort
of like making a deal with God. That's not in the גמרא
directly, but תוספות Tosafot, is saying that would be why the גמרא
reframed it as a נדר neder in order to help understand the
psychology. But yeah, I don't know. I mean, תוספות Tosafot in a
couple of places talks about these deals you're making with God, like
the גמרא we had earlier that said about a guy who said
I'll be a נזיר till I get to place X, that what
תוספות, that what the guy meant was, was that amount of time
because you're basically sort of telling God, God, if You protect me
on the journey, then I'll agree to be a נזיר for the
duration of the journey. So תוספות in a couple of places is
trying to get us into that type of deal-making psychology. Okay.
The cows when she says I could lift up the cow, that's
actually much less of a problem because it's its own will, it's
not making a תנאי. tnai.
Right, it's totally external to him. Right, yeah, right, exactly.
You just physically lift up the cow?
Yeah, why not? I mean, you know, not like you lift up
a thousand pounds, but you pull it and then it stands as
a result.
המשיח! Ha-mashiach! אמן כן יהי רצון! Amen ken yehi ratzon! Exactly!
It's משנה, the whole thing is linguistic, right? Yeah. So the נזירות
is to be closer to the divine, but they made a mistake,
it's closer to the bovine.
Thank you. I was waiting, I knew there was a joke at
the end of that lead-in there. Okay, fine.
I was at the door though.
Okay.
I had a friend who, I've still, who like 20 years ago
for פורים Purim put out this cover of a, of the new
Aviva Zornberg תורה Torah commentary on ויקרא Vayikra and it was called
'Bovines of Rupture'.
It was brilliant! It had a whole like description and blurbs. Anyway,
fine. Okay, and table of contents. Anyway, okay, so now the גמרא
says like this.
Okay,
fine. So now it's not the cow talking, it's you talking, you're
saying if it won't stand, and if you mean if I won't
be able to get it to stand, and that's a debate of
בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי. Fine. So the גמרא says
like this. אי הכי אימא סיפא. I kachi eima seifa. Wait a
minute, if you said I am a נזיר from wine and the
whole question was was your condition met, what do you do with
רבי יהודה at the end that says you're not a נזיר, you're
just forbidden to eat the meat? Right, that clearly means that you
weren't clear that you were going to be a נזיר from wine.
אמר רבי יהודה אף כשאמרו בית שמאי לא אמרו אלא באומר הרי
עלי קרבן הרי עלי קרבן. Amar Rabbi Yehuda af k’she’amru Beit Shammai
lo amru ela be’omer harei alai korban harei alai korban. So the
בית שמאי, even בית שמאי is only saying that the cow is
forbidden to you like a קרבן, even they wouldn't say you really
would be a נזיר. So how could that be if you explicitly
said you'll be a נזיר from wine and the whole thing with
the cow is just a weird condition? So the גמרא says: פרה
מי קא מתפיס בה מידי? Para mi ka matpis bah mididi? According
to your explanation, you're not making the cow forbidden, you're not being
מתפיס matpis it בנדר, be'neder, the cow was just some condition you
were making and you basically were saying you were going to be
a נזיר from wine. So that idea doesn't fit in with רבי
יהודה's desire to limit it just to the making the cow forbidden.
So, פרה מי קא מתפיס בה מידי? Para mi ka matpis bah
mididi? אלא כגון דאמר, Ela kegon de'amar, fine. Here's what you said:
הריני נזיר מבשרה. We're back to like we said before, right, saying
I'm a נזיר from the dates, you're saying I'm a נזיר from
the meat. And we're back to that whole debate of בית הלל
Beis Hillel and בית שמאי when you say I'm a נזיר from
X and X is completely irrelevant. בית שמאי says you are a
נזיר, בית הלל Beis Hillel says you're not, and רבי יהודה says
you're forbidden to eat that object. That's exactly the exact same issue
we had before about the dates. So that's what you said. You
said you're a נזיר from the meat, except we're still going to
hold on to our crazy תנאי. tnai. Okay. Okay, אם לא עמדה,
that's still this thing about the cow talking is that the cow
is saying I'll be a נזיר from the meat if I don't
stand. And עמדה and it stood מאליה. בית שמאי סברי טורפיה דהאי
גברא משום אוקמה בידיה, Beis Shammai savri turpei d'hai gavra mishum ukme
b'yadei,
your emphasis was if I can't get it to stand and in
the end והלו אוקמה, v'halo ukme, you didn't get it to stand,
so you are a נזיר. ובית הלל סברי, and בית הלל Beis
Hillel holds טורפיה דהאי גברא משום דרביעה, turpei d'hai gavra mishum darveia,
no,
your emphasis is that you're upset that it's crouched down, והא קמה
v'ha kama and it stood. It doesn't matter who got it to
stand, right? It doesn't matter who solved the problem, it was solved.
Okay, so now we're back to them arguing about a תנאי, tnai,
but we have now said that in order to explain רב יהודה,
Reb Yehuda, you didn't just say I'm a נזיר from one, you
said I'm a נזיר from its meat. So now the גמרא says
if you said you're a נזיר from its meat, what does the
תנאי tnai matter for בית הלל? So the גמרא says ובית הלל
סברי לא קמה הוי נזיר, u'Beis Hillel savri lo kama havei nazir,
wait one minute, בית הלל who would say that if it wouldn't
stand, if it actually remained crouched down you'd be a נזיר, that
it's all about the condition? So one minute, how could that be?
והאמר רבי בבשרא לא הוי נזיר, v'ha'amar Rebbi b'bisra lo havei nazir,
בית שמאי says that if a guy says I'm a נזיר from
the meat, which is what we had to say the case was,
you wouldn't be a נזיר regardless because a נזיר from a meat
is nonsense. So the גמרא says אלא לדבריהם דבית שמאי קאמרי, ela
l'divreihem d'Beis Shammai ka'amri, they're saying back according to בית שמאי's reasoning.
We're done, look, as far as we're concerned we've already explained our
position earlier when we were dealing with the dates. אפילו לא קמה
נמי לא הוי נזיר, afilu lo kama nami lo havei nazir, even
if it wouldn't get up you wouldn't be a נזיר because you
can't be נזיר from meat, can't be נזיר from dates, can't be
נזיר from a door, that's meaningless. I don't care if the condition
was met or wasn't met, you're not going to be a נזיר.
לדידכו דאמריתו הוי נזיר, l'didchu d'amritu havei nazir, according to you that
you guys say I'm a נזיר from meat it actually works and
you become a נזיר, okay, that's maybe in the previous משנה where
you said it without a condition, but אודו לן מיהא, odu lan
mei'ha, in this case concede to us דטורפיה דהאי גברא משום דרביעה
והא קמה, d'turpei d'hai gavra mishum darveia v'ha kama, this guy's focus
was it was crouched and it stood up so your condition wasn't
met because you said if it doesn't stand and it stood. So
at least you should concede even according to your idea that this
guy isn't a נזיר because the condition wasn't met. ובית שמאי, u'Beis
Shammai, and בית שמאי would say back לאו טורפיה דהאי גברא משום
אוקמה בידיה והלו אוקמה, lav turpei d'hai gavra mishum ukme b'yadei v'halo
ukme, no, it's not true, your focus is whether you'll get it
to stand and והלו אוקמה v'halo ukme you didn't, you weren't the
one who got it to stand, so therefore your condition was met
and therefore you are a נזיר. So basically in the end whatever
the crazy case of the cow is everybody agrees because it's exactly
the same structure of the משנה. You've got a cow here, you've
got בית שמאי saying you're a נזיר, בית הלל saying you're not,
and רב יהודה Reb Yehuda saying you can't eat the cow. Okay,
it's like some type of a skit, anyway, fine.
Okay, so which is exactly like the previous משנה when you say
I'm a נזיר from dates. בית שמאי says you're a נזיר, בית
הלל says you're not, and רב יהודה Reb Yehuda says don't eat
the dates. So clearly that's what the debate is going to boil
down to, effectively a guy saying I'm a נזיר from the meat
of the cow where בית שמאי says you are, בית הלל says
you're not, and רב יהודה Reb Yehuda says according to בית שמאי
don't eat the meat. So what do you do? What we're left
with is explaining this crazy initial story about the talking cow. So
the first explanation really is the simplest, is like whatever you said
about the talking cow or not you basically said I'll be a
נזיר from its meat if it stands and it stood. Okay, and
that's basically what's going on, fine. The cow is a little bit
of a distraction, but you just said if it stands and it
stood, everybody agrees the condition was met, what do you do with
that end statement I'm a נזיר from its meat? Okay, the next
explanation seems much more forced, it basically says it boils down to
the same point except it makes the condition not that you said
if it does stand I'll be a נזיר but you said if
it doesn't stand I'll be a נזיר and then introduces a new
debate about whether that condition was met, whether if it doesn't stand
means just if it doesn't stand and then the condition was not
met, or if it doesn't stand means if I'm not able to
get it to stand and then the condition was met, and so
it introduces an addition to the debate about the meat, a debate
about whether the condition was actually met or not. What that has
to do with talking cows and talking doors, I don't know, but
there you have it. Okay, and we were actually ends early today,
we should probably go on but I didn't prepare ahead so we're
going to end early, yes.
Do you have anything to say about this phrase that keeps on
repeating throughout this סוגיא? sugya?